Guide to the Transportation Collection 1751-1950 MS 035 MS 035 MS 035
Cornwall Historical Society
Transportation Collection
1751-1950
Cornwall Historical Society
Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941
MS 035
0.5 linear feet (1 box)
This collection is devoted to items related to the history of transportation in Cornwall.
Provenance
The items found in this collection were gathered by Cornwall historians E.C. Starr and Emily E. Marsh.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
This collection is devoted to items related to the history of transportation in Cornwall.
Sources:
Scope and Content Note
. The collection was formed from loose materials formerly contained in miscellaneous boxes. The materials in the collection relate to different types of transportation used in Cornwall during the period from 1751-1950.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by type of transportation then chronologically within each type of transportation.
The files are grouped into 3 series:
Railroads
Roads
Waterways
Railroads--Connecticut.; Transportation--Connecticut.; Housatonic Railroad; Housatonic River (Mass. and Conn.); Cornwall (Conn.); Pamphlets; Correspondence; Receipts (financial records); Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941
- Railroads
  - Copy of the contract for the construction of the Housatonic Rail Road, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Housatonic Railroad Co. receipt for coal from H. Hitchcock, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Housatonic Railroad Co. receipt for coal from First E. Society, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Notice to Housatonic Railroad stockholders, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Housatonic Railroad weekly ticket reports, 1879-1880 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Housatonic Railroad Co. receipt for reserved car from E.D. Benedict, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Copies of railroad timetables, 1889-1914 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - New Haven Railroad menu, with image of Cornwall covered bridge, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Housatonic Railroad Crossing Bell, 1920 - 1970 (Object 1)
    General
    This bell, likely installed around 1920, was one of many warning bells removed by the railroad during the 1980s due to upgrades. This bell had been installed at the West Cornwall train station.
- Roads
  - Survey book, 1751 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Index to Canaan and Litchfield Turnpike Co. records, 1803-1809 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Goshen and Sharon Turnpike stock certificates, 1808-1809 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Sharon and Cornwall Turnpike commissioner certificates, 1838-1839 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Selectmen’s notice of the discontinuation of Old Essex Hill Road, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Petition for town meeting to address poor road conditions, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence between E.C. Starr and S.G. Patterson, regarding road name origins, 1911-1915 (Box 1, Folder 17-20)
  - Letter sent to H. Swift about new road proposal, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Waterways
  - State report on the construction of Ousatonic Valley Canal, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Booklet, “Proposals for the Stock of the Ousatonic Canal Company", 1822 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Record of town vote taken, approving the construction of a canal, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 24)